Register of the Loyd Wright Papers, 1924-1971
Hoover Institution Archives
Loyd Wright papers,
1924-1971
82071
Wright, Loyd, 1892-1974
45 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (18.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, testimony, reports, conference proceedings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to internal security in the United States, international law, law in the United States, and California politics.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
American Bar Association; International Bar Association; United States. Commission on Government Security; Internal security--United States; Law--United States; Subversive activities--United States; California--Politics and government; United States--Politics and government; International law; Lawyers
Biographical Note
1892 Dec. 24 Born, San Jacinto, California
1915-c. 1970 Practiced law in Los Angeles, California
1921-1936 Lecturer, School of Law, University of Southern California
1937-1938 President, Los Angeles Bar Association
1940-1941 President, State Bar of California
1942-c. 1945 Member, Alien Enemy Appeals Board
1944-1951 Chairman, California State Racing Board
1953-1954 Member, Commission on Judicial and Congressional Salaries
1954-1955 President, American Bar Association
1954-1964 President, International Bar Association
1955-1957 Chairman, Commission on Government Security
1962 Candidate, U.S. Senate
1974 Oct. 22 Died, Hemet, California
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, c. 1955-1968. (Box 1)
  Memoranda, clipping, correspondence, list, and biographical sketches. Arranged chronologically.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1969. (Boxes 1-18)
  Typescripts, printed copies, clippings, flyers, speeches and statements by others, correspondence, programs, serial issues, press releases, procedure manuals, newsletters, pamphlets, flyers, reports, notes, position statements, draft legislation, resolutions, legal briefs, printed articles, and hearing transcripts. Arranged chronologically.
- AMERICAN BAR ASSOCIATION, 1947-1968. (Boxes 18-24)
  Correspondence, reports, minutes, serial issues, memoranda, biographical sketches, by-laws, press releases, directories, speeches and statements, budgets, grant applications, draft legislation, transcripts, articles of incorporation, circulars, newsletters, printed articles, clippings, leaflets, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- INTERNATIONAL BAR ASSOCIATION, 1953-1971. (Boxes 25-32)
  Correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, printed articles, membership lists, financial material, speeches and statements, serial issues, reports, conference material, press releases, by-laws, resolutions, agenda, bulletins, and miscellany. Arranged by physical form.
- POLITICAL FILE, 1924-1969. (Boxes 32-38)
  Speeches and statements, circulars, draft legislation, newsletters, legal documents, pamphlets, reports, press releases, serial issues, clippings, correspondence, campaign material, lists, leaflets, memoranda, flyers, notes, itineraries, voting records, transcripts, position papers, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1969. (Boxes 38-45)
  Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, agenda, clippings, notes, newsletters, memoranda, conference material, reports, draft and final copies of legislation, pamphlets, legal documents, bulletins, hearing transcripts, lists, rules, programs, by-laws, resolutions, speeches and statements, circulars, financial charts, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, c. 1943-1958. (10.A-V)
  Photographs of Loyd Wright and others, primarily at meetings and conferences; also includes one print of a horse race, and a negative of a certificate.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, c. 1955-1968.
  - Memoranda, clipping, correspondence, list, and biographical sketches (Box 1., Folder 1)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1969
  - General. Background material
    - General. Clippings, flyers, speeches and statements (by Barry Goldwater, Herbert Brownell, Jr., William Tompkins, Robert Welch, Dean Acheson, Thomas Dodd, Ronald Reagan, Edwin A. Walker, Carl Sandburg, and others), reports, newsletters, legal briefs, statement of principles, press releases, printed articles (by Leslie R. Groves, Joseph Ball, Ezra T. Benson, Maurice Stans, George Ball, Raymond Moley, Arthur Radford, and others), draft legislation, resolutions, notes, pamphlets, hearing transcripts, serial issues, lists, and agenda. Includes material relating to the judiciary, constitutional law, the Supreme Court, civil rights, internal security, the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), organized crime, communism, economics, and foreign affairs
      - Undated (Box 1., Folder 2)
      - 1928-1954 (Folder 3-5)
      - 1955-1960 (Box 2., Folder 1-5)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 3., Folder 1-5)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 4., Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence. Includes Clarence Manion, Louis B. Nichols, and others, 1954-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Undated and fragments
    - General (Folder 5)
    - American Bar Association (Folder 6)
  - 1940-1951. Typescripts, printed copies, correspondence, clippings, programs, and printed material (Box 5., Folder 1-8)
  - 1952-1954 Sept. 13. Typescripts, printed copies, speeches by others, printed material, and a serial issue; includes testimony prepared for the Senate Judiciary Committee (Box 6., Folder 1-11)
  - 1954 Sept. 24-1955 Feb. 8. Correspondence, typescripts, printed copies, serial issues, press releases, and printed material (Box 7., Folder 1-9)
  - 1955 Feb. 25-April 22. Typescripts, correspondence, clippings, programs, serial issues, and printed material (Box 8., Folder 1-8)
  - 1955 May-June. Typescripts, correspondence, clippings, procedure manuals, and printed material (Box 9., Folder 1-9)
  - 1955 July-1956 March. Typescripts, correspondence, serial issue, and miscellany (Box 10., Folder 1-10)
  - 1956 April-1957 Oct. 16. Typescripts, correspondence, newsletter, programs, printed material, and clippings; includes testimony before the House Post Office and Civil Service Committee (Box 11., Folder 1-17)
  - 1957 Oct. 23-1958 March 27. Typescripts, serial issues, printed material, clippings, programs, and miscellany (Box 12., Folder 1-10)
  - 1958 April 9-1959 May. Typescripts, programs, pamphlets, clippings, notes, printed material, and miscellany (Box 13., Folder 1-11)
  - 1958 Oct. 23-1959 May. Typescripts, clippings, serial issues, newsletter, draft legislation, press releases, reports, flyers, printed material, and miscellany; includes testimony before the House Post Office and Civil Service Committee and the Senate Judiciary Committee (Box 14., Folder 1-8)
  - 1959 June-1960 May. Typescripts, pamphlets, correspondence, newsletters, notes, clippings, flyers, and miscellany; includes material relating to the World Court (Connally amendment) (Box 15., Folder 1-11)
  - 1960 June 3-1961 Nov. Typescripts, clippings, pamphlets, correspondence, newsletters, speeches and statements by others, and miscellany (Box 16., Folder 1-11)
  - 1961 Nov. 1-1964 Dec. Correspondence, clippings, typescripts, position statements, and printed material; primarily relates to Loyd Wright's 1962 California Republican senatorial primary campaign (Box 17., Folder 1-17)
  - 1965-1967. Typescripts, draft legislation, statements by others, newsletters, correspondence, pamphlets, flyers, and printed material; includes testimony before the House Un-American Activities Committee (Box 18., Folder 1-8)
  - 1968-1969. Legislation, correspondence, typescripts, printed material, and miscellany; includes testimony before the House Un-American Activities Committee (Box 19., Folder 1-2)
- AMERICAN BAR ASSOCIATION
  - General
    - General. Serial issues and minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 19., Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1955-1960 (Folder 4)
      - Presidency, Loyd Wright's election to
        - 1951-1952 (Folder 5)
        - 1954 (Box 20., Folder 1-2)
    - Meeting material
      - 1955. Correspondence (including Richard M. Nixon and Earl Warren), printed material, reports, memoranda, biographical sketches, and miscellany (Folder 3)
      - 1958
        - General. By-laws, press release, correspondence, program, and printed material (Folder 4)
        - Reports (Box 21., Folder 1)
      - 1960-1966. Correspondence and programs (Folder 2)
    - Membership material. Directories, reports, correspondence, memoranda, and printed material, c. 1949-1958 (Folder 3-5)
  - Banking and business law. Index, serials, and correspondence, 1954-1961 (Box 22., Folder 1)
  - Constitutional Revision, Committee on. Correspondence, by-laws, and membership lists, 1960-1962 (Folder 2-3)
  - Criminal justice. Report, correspondence (with William J. Donovan, Evelle Younger, Robert H. Jackson, Earl Warren, and others), printed material, speeches, press releases, memoranda, and minutes, 1953-1955 (Folder 4)
  - Endowment
    - General. Articles of incorporation and by-laws, minutes, printed material, budgets, reports, grant applications, and memoranda, 1960-1968 (Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 23., Folder 1-5)
    - Meeting material, 1964-1968 (Box 24., Folder 1-2)
  - Essay contest. Correspondence, 1955 (Folder 3)
  - Examiners. Report and correspondence, 1954-1955 (Folder 4)
  - Federal judiciary. Primarily correspondence; also includes reports, memoranda, draft legislation, recommendations on appointments, and transcripts, 1951-1954 (Folder 5-6)
  - Memorials. Correspondence and lists, 1954-1956 (Box 25., Folder 1)
  - Mental Illness and Health, Joint Commission on. Correspondence, by-laws, certificate of incorporation, and a list, 1954-1955 (Folder 2)
  - Military Justice, Committee on. Correspondence, 1954 (Folder 3)
  - Model Corporation Acts project. Report and correspondence, 1955-1958 (Folder 4)
  - Municipal law. Newsletter, circular, and a printed article, 1954-1955 (Folder 5)
  - National Association of County and Prosecuting Attorneys. Correspondence and a circular, 1955 (Folder 6)
  - National Association of Women Lawyers. Correspondence and a serial issue, 1955 (Folder 7)
  - National Conference of Lawyers and Realtors. Letter, 1954 (Folder 8)
  - New York Bar Association. Reports, serial issues, correspondence, speech, and miscellany, 1953-1957 (Folder 9)
  - Patent law. Report and correspondence, 1954 (Folder 10)
  - Peace and Law, Committee on. Reports, statement, and correspondence, 1947-1959 (Folder 11)
  - Politics. Correspondence, clippings, and a leaflet, 1953-1955 (Folder 12)
  - Postal Regulations, Special Committee on. Letter, 1954 (Folder 13)
- INTERNATIONAL BAR ASSOCIATION, 1953-1971
  - General. Membership lists, newsletters, printed articles, speech, financial material, serial issues, constitution, reports, conference material, press releases, and miscellany, 1953-1970 (Box 26., Folder 1-4)
  - Applications. Primarily correspondence and miscellany, 1958-1965 (Box 27., Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda
    - 1957-1958 June (Folder 4-6)
    - 1958 July-1961 Dec. (Box 28., Folder 1-4)
    - 1963-1971 (Box 29., Folder 1-3)
  - Meeting material
    - 1954-1955. Correpondence, memoranda, minutes, constitution and by-laws, 1954-1956 (Folder 4)
    - 1956. Correspondence, newsletters, memoranda, minutes, resolutions, program, and miscellany, 1955-1956 (Box 30., Folder 1-3)
    - 1957 March. Agenda, newsletter, memoranda, minutes, and correspondence, 1957 (Folder 4)
    - 1957 Nov. Reports, newsletters, agenda, and bulletins, 1957 (Folder 5)
    - 1958
      - General. Printed articles, newsletters, speeches, clippings, minutes, and lists, 1957-1958 (Box 31., Folder 1)
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957-1960 (Folder 2)
    - 1960. Memoranda, correspondence, program, minutes, resolutions, and reports, 1960-1961 (Folder 3)
    - 1962 Jan. Agenda, correspondence, minutes, lists, and miscellany, 1961-1962 (Folder 4)
    - 1962 July
      - General. Printed articles, clippings, lists, reports, newsletters, serial issue, and minutes, 1962 (Folder 5)
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1962-1963 (Box 32., Folder 1)
    - 1963 May. Correspondence, agenda, rules, and reports, 1963 (Folder 2)
    - 1963 July. Resolutions, reports, declaration of principles, printed articles, correspondence, pamphlet, program, and miscellany, 1961-1963 (Folder 3)
    - 1963 Dec. Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Folder 4)
    - 1964. Correspondence and miscellany, 1962-1964 (Folder 5)
    - 1966. Printed articles, program, resolution, reports, agenda, and miscellany, 1966 (Folder 6)
    - 1968. Agenda, newsletter, schedule, and correspondence, 1968 (Box 33., Folder 1)
    - 1969. Agenda and miscellany, 1969 (Folder 2)
    - 1970. Agenda, minutes, constitution and by-laws, 1970 (Folder 3)
- POLITICAL FILE, 1924-1969
  - General. Speeches and statements (by Harry S. Truman, Thomas Dodd, Ezra Taft Benson, Eddie Rickenbacker and others), circulars, leaflets, draft legislation, newsletters, legal documents, pamphlets, reports, press releases, serial issues, and clippings; includes material relating to foreign relations, the United Nations, internal security, economics, education, Medicare, the Congo, and Cuba
    - 1944-1949 (Box 33., Folder 4-5)
    - 1958-1962 Feb. (Box 34., Folder 1-4)
    - 1962 March-1969 (Box 35., Folder 1-2)
  - Los Angeles. Excerpts from the city charter relating to procedures for recalling the mayor, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Nixon, Richard M. Correspondence (with Richard Nixon, Maurice Stans, Herbert Klein and others), guest lists, campaign material, and miscellany, 1951-1969 (Folder 4)
  - Pitchess, Peter J. Correspondence and a list relating to a campaign for Los Angeles County sheriff, 1958 (Folder 5)
  - Rafferty, Max. Correspondence and campaign material relating to the 1968 California Republican senatorial primary, 1967 (Folder 6)
  - Republican Party
    - General. Correspondence (with Caspar Weinberger, and others), form letters, leaflets, memoranda, and lists; primarily relates to California Republican committees and political campaigns, 1944-1968 (Folder 7-9)
    - Republican National Committee. Lists, newsletters, clippings, and a press release, 1945-1946 (Box 36., Folder 1)
    - Republican National Convention. Correspondence (with Richard Nixon, Dwight Eisenhower, Thomas Kuchel, Sherman Adams, and others), press releases, circulars, flyers, and miscellany, 1956 (Folder 2)
    - Republican Associates. Newsletters, form letter, correspondence, statement of principles, and reports, 1958-1964 (Folder 3)
  - Senatorial campaign, California, 1962
    - General
      - General. Newsletters, clippings, questionnaires, campaign material, speeches and statements (by Ezra Taft Benson, Strom Thurmond, Thomas Dodd, James Utt, Ben Moreell, and others), serial issues, pamphlets, and flyers, 1961-1962 (Folder 4-5)
      - Campaign material. Lists, press releases, correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed material, circulars, and miscellany, 1962 (Folder 6)
      - Campaign material (Box 37., Folder 1-2)
      - Clippings, 1962 (Folder 3)
      - Correspondence and memoranda. Includes Murray Chotiner, William Knowland, Ezra T. Benson, Richard Nixon, Barry Goldwater, Walter Judd, Walter Knott, Thomas Dodd, Paul McCloskey, Jr., Otis Chandler, and others
        - 1961 Dec.-1962 April (Folder 4-6)
        - 1962 May-Sept. (Box 38., Folder 1-3)
      - Itineraries (Folder 4)
    - Jarvis, Howard. Speeches (by Ezra T. Benson, and Howard Jarvis), correspondence, flyers, campaign material, transcripts, and legal documents, 1924-1962 (Folder 5)
    - Kuchel, Thomas. Voting records, clippings, correspondence, broadcast transcripts, a circular, and printed material, 1953-1962 (Folder 6)
    - Reagan, Ronald. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, and a flyer, 1962 (Box 39., Folder 1)
  - Warren, Earl. Correspondence, lists, speeches, campaign material, form letters, memoranda, position papers, press releases, and notes, 1943-1953; primarily relates to the 1946 California gubernatorial campaign and judicial appointments (Folder 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1969
  - General. Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, agenda, and miscellany, 1961-1969; primarily relates to various conservative citizens organizations (Box 39., Folder 3-4)
  - Alien Enemy Appeal Board. Correspondence (with the War Relocation Authority, Francis Biddle, and others), program statement, clipping, notes, miscellany, and typescript copies of statements by Japanese-American internees, 1942-1944 (Box 40., Folder 1)
  - Aviation Project Committee, California State Reconstruction and Reemployment Commission. Newsletter, conference material, memoranda, correspondence, lists, reports, draft and final copies of legislation, pamphlets, and printed material, 1945 (Folder 2-3)
  - Bricker Amendment. Correspondence (with John Bricker, John Stennis, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Sherman Adams, Herbert Brownell, Jr., Walter George, and others), clippings, memoranda, and a report, 1954-1959; relates to congressional attempts to limit executive treaty-making power (Folder 4)
  - California Horse Racing Board. Correspondence, memoranda, legal documents, reports, bulletins, hearing transcripts, lists, clippings, newsletters, rules, press releases, programs, and miscellany
    - 1939-1945 July (Folder 5)
    - 1945 Aug.-Dec. (Box 41., Folder 1-4)
  - Commission on Judicial and Congressional Salaries. Legislation, correspondence (with Richard Nixon and others), clipping, and resolutions, 1953-1954 (Box 42., Folder 1-2)
  - Congregational Church. Reports, by-laws, pamphlets, a printed article (with translation) relating to communism in Latin America, correspondence, and financial material, 1940-1945 (Folder 3)
  - Connally Amendment
    - General. Reports, clippings, speeches and statements, newsletters, printed articles, press releases, resolutions, and circulars; relates to the jurisdiction of the World Court
      - 1959-1960 (Folder 4)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 43., Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and memoranda. Includes Richard Nixon, Karl Mundt, Strom Thurmond, Robert Finch, and others, 1959-1961 (Folder 2-4)
  - Crime. Letter, clipping and a report (by David A. Pine) relating to a government commission on crime in Washington, D.C., 1967 (Box 44., Folder 1)
  - Judiciary. Primarily corrrespondence (with George Murphy, the White House, Ronald Reagan, and others), relating to appointments and meetings, 1966-1969 (Folder 2)
  - Loyalty-security issues
    - General. Correspondence (includes letters to editors, to Melvin Laird, and the White House), draft legislation, resolutions, reports, press releases, clippings, an affidavit, newsletters, legal brief, speeches and statements, and hearing transcripts, 1953-1968; includes material relating to congressional internal security committees, the Supreme Court, immigration, and foreign relations (Folder 3-5)
    - Commission on Government Security. Letter, hearing transcript (excerpts), recommendations, and a press release, 1956-1957 (Box 45., Folder 1)
  - Pornography. Correspondence, legal documents, clippings, resolutions, speeches (E. Richard Barnes), memoranda, reports, newsletters, pamphlet, and press releases, 1963-1969; relates to proposed anti-pornography legislation in the California State Assembly (Folder 2)
  - Roberts, Arch E. Correspondence, flyers, clippings, miscellany, and circulars, 1966-1967; relates to a group called the Committee for the Constitution (Folder 3)
  - Russia. Typescript text of the Soviet constitution, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - War Savings Committee. Correspondence (with the Treasury Department and others), financial charts, notes, memoranda, speech, and miscellany, 1942-1943 (Folder 5)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, c. 1943-1958.
  - Photographs of Loyd Wright and others, primarily at meetings and conferences; also includes one print of a horse race, and a negative of a certificate. (Folder 10. A-V)